Society of Protozoologists records
Society of Protozoologists records
1947-2012
1947 2012
Coll013
Society of Protozoologists
30 boxes (31.25 linear feet)
30 boxes
31.25 linear feet
Files documenting the development and growth of the Society of Protozoologists from its founding in 1947. The organization approved a name change to International Society of Protistologists (ISOP) in 2005. Collection contains records relating to society history, affiliated societies, and the Executive Committee, including: membership files, meetings, correspondence, publications (such as the Journal of Protozoology and the Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology), pamphlets, newsletters, audit reports, bank statements, reconciliation reports and invoices.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
This collection of records of the Society of Protozoologists 1947-2012 documents the origins of the Society and its significant growth in membership. The records are arranged in five series: History, Executive Committee, Membership, Meetings, Publications, Affiliated Societies and Miscellaneous.
The History Series contains information about the early years of the organization. The original Constitution and Bylaws are included as well as a documents concerning Constitution revisions.
Since there was no central organizational office, the records were kept by officers of the Society at various locations during their time in office. Therefore the bulk of Society records can be found under the Executive Committee Series: President, Secretary and Treasurer. The Secretary was responsible for membership, meeting arrangements, meeting agendas and minutes, and the comprehensive coordination of Society business. General correspondence may also contain committee reports, meeting arrangements, and membership and material pertaining to election issues. Treasurer records consist of correspondence and financial documents. The financial records include general deposits and disbursements, bank statements, audits, invoices, fund account records as well as some information concerning membership. Allen Press published the journal and also had the responsibility of membership payments and mailing out the Journal to Society members. Some financial, membership and journal matters can be found in Allen Press files of the Executive Committee, Membership and Publications Series. Membership lists, member status and payment records are in the Membership Series.
Business/Membership Meeting files include correspondence about meeting arrangements, agendas and travel grant matters. Committee reports, minutes and occasionally presentation abstracts are included in the files. There is a complete run of all annual business/membership meetings from 1954 to 1990 containing varying amounts of materials from each meeting The Executive Committee meetings are complete from 1954 until 1990 with the exception of 1958.
The Publications Series contains educational pamphlets, a few Society newsletters and meeting programs published by the Society. A complete run of the Society’s Journal of Protozoology, which was renamed The Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology in 1993, is available from 1954-1994. Financial information concerning Journal publishing, design and subscriptions are included in the Series.
Affiliated Societies files contain correspondence about joint meetings and common scientific objectives, minutes from affiliated society meetings attended by Society of Protzoologists representatives and publications.
The Miscellaneous Series contains numerous photographs which, while not identified, were most likely taken at Society meetings. Recording tapes and two floppy disks concerning Society meetings are in this Series. Also included is a slide collection of Dr. Eugene Bovee.
Addendum 1 contains financial records belonging to the Executive Committee Series and Treasurer Subseries. The majority are a complete run of income receipts and statements from 1990/7 – 2000/6.
The Society of Protozoologists was established to promote a closer association among all those interested in any kind of protozoological research. The Society’s Constitution states that, “The aim of the Society was to form an association of workers for the presentation and discussion of new and important facts and problems in protozoology and for the adoption of such measures as will tend to advance protozoological science.” Therefore, there are no restrictions regarding age, academic degrees, nationality or professional occupation for membership. Six categories of membership are available: full, student, spouse, corresponding, emeritus and honorary. Membership in the Society peaked at 1300 or so members by the late 1960’s and early 1970’s and then leveled off to its present level of some 800 to 900 members in the 1990’s.
The organization was founded December 19, 1947 in Chicago, Illinois during an informal gathering of interested biologists while they were there attending the American Association for the Advancement of Science meeting. The first slate of officers was elected at that time. They were as follows: R.F. Nigrelli, President; B.B. Morgan, Vice-President; and T.L. Jahn, Secretary-Treasurer. Additional members of the Executive Committee elected were: D.L. Hopkins, R.R. Kudo, J.L.Mohr, K.L. Osterud and R.M. Stabler. A Constitutional Committee was composed of John L. Mohr, P. Hall and K.L. Osterud.
The first formal meeting of the entire Society was held on December 28, 1949 in conjunction with the AAAS meeting in New York City. There were fifty attending members who considered the issue of the Society’s Constitution and Bylaws and the established the Resolutions Committee, Nominating Committee, Program Committee and Auditing Committee. Annual Membership/Business meetings continued thereafter and were generally held in conjunction with a variety of biological science associations. Those organizations included the American Association for Advancement of Science, American Institute of Biological Sciences (most often,) American Society of Zoologists, and the Phycology Society of America. The Executive Committee (consisting of officers, Section representatives, and five elected members) generally meets during the annual membership/business meetings, but occasionally meet in supplementary sessions. Additionally, there were ten international conferences in a variety of world destinations. These were held every four to five years beginning in 1961. Some times the international conferences were held in conjunction with the annual meetings while other years domestic annual meetings were held at a different time.
In 1951 the Journal and Editorial Committees were established with the express task of formulating and overseeing the development of a scholarly journal for the Society. The first volume of the quarterly published Journal of Protozoology made its debut in February of 1954. William Trager was the Journal’s first editor. He served in this capacity from 1954-1965. The journal was regarded as a highly respected outlet for original research papers in areas of descriptive and experimental nature. In later years a supplement was added to the Journal, which contained the programs and abstracts of the annual meetings and officer and committee reports. Periodically membership lists and reprintings or revisions of the Constitution were also included in the Supplement. In 1989 the Journal began to be printed bimonthly instead of quarterly. In 1993 the name of the Journal of Protozoology was changed to the Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology, which remains its present name.
In addition the Society began to publish a the Newsletter in 1976 which was usually edited by the office of the Secretary. It contained announcements and other news of general interest to the membership such as information on future meeting sites, winners of awards, workshop notices, obituary tributes and letters form members. In 1991 an official editor was separately designated to oversee the newsletter’s publication. At this time the formal minutes of the Executive Committee meeting and annual Business Meetings, some committee and Section reports, constitutional revisions, international news and bits of “protozoology humor” were added to the newsleter. This allowed those members (Corresponding and Emeritus Memberships) who didn’t receive the Journal to be more informed about the Society’s activities.
The Society of Protozoology has always advocated an international outlook and attitude in membership and organizational affiliations. In 1961 the Society created a membership category called Corresponding Membership to encourage international growth. This allowed members residing outside the United States to have full participation in Society affairs (with the exception of receiving the Journal) at a reduced rate. Since its inception the Society has had more non-US members than any other “American” biological society, with members joining from over forty countries. The British Section was the first to be established in 1962. Other affiliated foreign sections have formed in Israel, Japan, Hungary, Scandinavia, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Germany, Italy, Brazil, Argentina, India, Mexico and China. Sectional representatives became voting members of the Executive Committee; and since the 1960’s the office of Vice President has always been filled by a non-American who has full membership. Sections were also formed in France and the Soviet Union, but neither group has chosen to formally become a part of the Society.
The Society has established five funded awards beginning with Richard P. Hall Memorial Fund in 1969, which was awarded to students in order to help with publishing costs. In 1976 the Seymour H. Hutner Young Investigator Prize was established by Hutner and his friends to acknowledge a young scientist not long out of his/her Ph.D. for outstanding research on the “cutting edge” of some field of protozoology. Students of Dr. Theodore Louis Jahn established an award in his name shortly before his death in 1979. This was a cash prize given yearly to a student member of the Society who presented the best poster or research paper at a Society meeting. The final two awards were established during the 1990’s. The George G. Holz, Jr. and Robert L. Conner Travel Award was created to provide travel awards to students and young investigators that would facilitate their participation in Society meetings. The John O. Corliss Ciliate Systematics Award was established to recognize a young ciliatologist authoring a published research paper in ciliate taxonomy judged to be the most worthy. The Awards Committee has the responsibility of recommending to the Executive Committee (for their ultimate approval) those people chosen for the awards.
The Society currently is challenged by declining membership. This is thought to be in part due to the trend toward more specialized scientific organizations and perhaps by the needed increase in membership dues. Currently there is discussion concerning possible merger of the Society with another biological society. The Society is now called the International Society of Protistologists.
This collection is organized into seven series. Series II and IV are further divided into subseries.
Series I. History
Series II. Executive Committee
President
Secretary
Treasurer
Tellers Committee
Series III. Membership
Series IV. Meetings
Annual Business/Membership
Executive Committee
Series V. Publications
Series VI. Affiliated Societies
Series VII. Miscellaneous
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
The collection came to UMBC Special Collections in two acquisitions. The first was accession number MSS 97-11 consisting of 16 boxes plus 47 bound and loose journals. The material dates from 1947 to 1990. It was transferred in March 1997 from Dr. Bruce Hill at Mt. Vernon College, Washington, D. C. The second acquisition came from Dr. Susan Langreth at the Herbert School of Medicine in Bethesda, Md. This consisted of three boxes of general records dating from 1984 to 1990. The acquisition number is SARCV 2000-13.
Addendum: A third donation of records was received after the earlier accessions had been processed. Accession SARCV 2001-04, consisting of 2 record cartons of materials, was donated by Dr. John Kloetzel on June 5, 2001.
Addendum: Records relating to the production of the Journal of Eukaryotic Microbiology were donated in 2012 by editor Denis Lynn.
International Society of Protistologists; Society of Protozoologists Archives; Protozoology Societies, etc.
International Society of Protistologists homepage (formerly Society of Protozoologists). Accessed November 18, 2015.
- Series I. History, 1949-1991; 4 folders (.25 linear feet)
  History files are arranged in date order and consist of items that officers deemed important in the organization's history.
  - General 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General 1959-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Constitution 1971-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Executive Committee, 1947-1995; 439 folders (14.9 linear feet)
  Executive Committee files are arranged into 3 sub-series by title; President, Secretary and Treasurer. General correspondence is in date order followed by subject files arranged in alpha order. The Treasurer subseries also contains the financial records. They arranged in subject files and then in date order.
  - Subseries II.A. President, 1964-1995; 16 folders (.55 linear feet)
    President files consist of correspondence files which are in date order. They are followed by subject files arranged in alpha order.
    - Correspondence 1964/11 - 1979/12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1980/1 - 1980/12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1981/1 - 1981/12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1989/1 - 1989/12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1990/1 - 1990/12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1994/1 - 1994/12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence 1995/1 - 1995/12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/American Association for the Advancement of Science 1981/5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Sciences 1980/7 - 1983/7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1984/11 1985/5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Committee on Constitutional Revision 1980/7 - 1980/9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/Committee on Systematics & Evolution 1980/1- 1980/12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/International Union of Biological Science 1967/1- 1968/12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/Travel Grants for 1981 Warsaw Meeting 1980/9 - 1981/12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/University Microfilm International 1980/1 - 1980/12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/V.President 1984/4 - 1984/8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Subseries II.B. Secretary, 1947-1990; 191 folders (8.25 linear feet)
    Secretary files consist of general correspondence files which are arranged in date order followed by subject files arranged in alpha order. Correspondence files may include committee and financial reports, Journal business, membership matters and information regarding Society meetings.
    - Correspondence 1947/1 - 1951/12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence 1952/1 - 1959/7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence 1959/8 - 1960/3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence 1960/5 - 1960/8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence 1960/9 - 1960/10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence 1960/11 - 1960/12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence 1961/1 - 1961/2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence 1961/3 - 1961/12 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence 1962/1 - 1962/12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence 1966/4 - 1968/9 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence 1969/6 - 1970/10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence 1971/1 - 1972/10 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence 1973/2 - 1974/2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence 1974/3 - 1974/5 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence 1974/6 - 1976/5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence 1977/1 - 1978/12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence 1979/1 - 1980/12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1982/1 - 1985/12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1986/1 - 1986/12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1987/1 - 1987/12 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1988/1 - 1988/12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1989/1 - 1990/12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Advertising 1983/10 - 1984/2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/Agricultural Research Institute 1971/7 ֱ973/2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press (Arly Allen) 1970/9 - 1972/11 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press (Chris Niemoeller) 1972/1 - 1973/12 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press (Chris Niemoeller) 1974/1 ֱ979/9 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press 1974/1 - 1976/5 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press 1977/7 - 1983/5 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Allen Press 1985/10 - 1990/9 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/American Association for the Advancement of Science 1954/8 - 1966/6 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/American Association for the Advancement of Science 1967/11 - 1973/12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/American Association for the Advancement of Science 1974/4 - 1979/10 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/American Association for the Advancement of Science 1985/9 - 1987/5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Science 1953/1 - 1955/12 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Science 1956/1 - 1959/12 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Science 1960/1 - 1969/12 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Science 1970/1 - 1981/12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence/American Institute of Biological Science (Meeting 1979) 1979/3 - 1979/6 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence/American Type Culture Association 1972/12 - 1985/3 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence/Auditing Committee 1956/3 - 1956/12 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence/Awards Committee 1986/8 - 1988/3 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence/Balamuth, William 1965/7 - 1965/12 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence/Balamuth, William 1968/7 ֱ970/6 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence/Balamuth, William 1970/7 - 1973/10 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence/Bamforth, Samuel 1997/9 - 1979/9 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence/Band, Neal 1972/10 - 1973/1 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence/Berger, Jacques 1964/12 - 1967/5 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence/Berger, Jacques 1967/11 - 1969/5 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence/Board of Review 1988/11 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence/Bovee, Eugene 1970/7 - 1979/10 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence/Bradbury, Phyllis 1968/9 - 1973/7 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence/Brazilian Section 1971/4 - 1973/7 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence/British Section 1962/11 - 1966/6 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence/British Section 1968/3 - 1979/6 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence/Brochure Requests 1970/7 - 1973/10 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence/Burchill, Brower 1978/8 - 1979/10 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence/Burchill, Brower 1983/6 - 1985/4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence/Burchill, Brower 1985/8 - 1990/5 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence/Business Advertising Committee 1974/12 - 1978/9 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Business Advertising Committee 1990/5 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1961/10 ֱ963/6 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1963/9 - 1964/7 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1964/10 - 1965/7 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1965/8 - 1966/10 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/Committee Appointments 1978/10 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Committees 1980 1980/2 - 1980/9 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Committees 1981 1981/10 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Committees 1982 & 1983 1982/1 - 1983/9 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/Committee Reports 1989 1989/7 - 1989/8 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/Conney, Robert 1974/9 - 1977/7 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/Constitutional Amendment 1961/1 - 1962/1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/Constitution & By Law Committee 1964/9 - 1966/6 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/Constitution Revision 1969/11 - 1970/2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/Constitution Revision 1979/11- 1988/10 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence/Corliss, John 1953/3-1962/7 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence/Corliss, John 1970/5-1973/8 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence/Corliss, John 1975/10 - 1976/8 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence/Cosgrove, William 1968/10 - 1973/1 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence/Culture Collections 1961/10 - 1961/12 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence/Czechoslovakian Section 1970/11 - 1979/3 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence/Diller, William 1954/9 - 1955/12 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence/Diller, William 1956/1 - 1957/10 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence/Education Committee 1973/1 - 1978/12 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence/Education Committee 1980/7 - 1987/11 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1981 1981/1 - 1981/3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1982 1982/3 - 1983/4 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1985 1985/6 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1986 1985/10 - 1986/6 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1987 1986/8 - 1987/6 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence/Elections 1989 & 1990 1989/1 - 1990/7 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1962/6 - 1963/12 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1973/1 - 1973/12 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1974/1 - 1974/12 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1975/1 - 1978/2 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1978/3 - 1979/5 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1982/8 - 1983/6 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1883/12 ֱ984/10 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1988/5 - 1988/7 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee 1990/1 - 1990/6 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence/Executive Committee Mail Outs 1968/8 - 1973/10 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence/Film Industry 1963/11 - 1966/8 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence/Foreign Sections 1984/3 - 1986/2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Frankel, George 1989/11 - 1990/7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/French Section 1975/2 - 1978/6 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/French Section 1982/10 - 1987/4 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Grain, J. 1970/4 - 1973/10 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/Gray, Peter 1961/11 - 1962/5 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/ German Section 1977/3 - 1977/4 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Hall Fund 1969/9 - 1972/10 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Honorary Membership 1955/10 - 1975/12 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Honorary Membership 1976/7 - 1981/12 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/Honigberg, B. (Journal Editor) 1965/1 - 1976/2 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/Honigberg, B. (Pres.) 1965/8 - 1966/9 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/Hull, R. (Pres.) 1969/1 - 1970/11 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/Hutner, S. (Pres.) 1961/10 - 1962/9 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/Hutner, S. (Special Publications) 1967/8 - 1976/12 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/Hutner, S. 1988/9 (Box 4, Folder 21)